Guide to the George William Hughes Britt papers, 1942-1953, bulk 1942-1944 RL.00152
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
George William Hughes Britt papers
1942-1953
1942-1944
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Britt, George, 1895-1988
RL.00152
1.2 Linear Feet 4 boxes Approximately 900 items
Collection includes correspondence, memoranda, intelligence, and statistical reports, reminiscences, news clippings, photographs, and financial papers (primarily 1942-1944) from his employment by the U.S. Office of War Information. Includes correspondence between Britt and the American ambassador in Turkey, Laurence A. Steinhardt. Contains legal papers, correspondence, and clippings relating to Karl and Stella von Kleczkowski; he was a former German espionage agent in Turkey who turned to the Allied cause in 1943.
Access Restrictions
Collection is restricted.
Provenance
The George William Hughes Britt papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift in 1990.
Biographical Note
George W. H. (William Hughes) Britt, born in Kentucky, was an educator, editor, journalist, and author. During World War II he was employed by the United States Office of War Information, Overseas Operations Branch, first in Beirut and later Istanbul.
Collection Overview
Collection includes correspondence, memoranda, intelligence, and statistical reports, reminiscences, news clippings, photographs, and financial papers (primarily 1942-1944) from his employment by the U.S. Office of War Information in Beirut and Cairo.
Also includes correspondence between Britt and the American ambassador in Turkey, Laurence A. Steinhardt. Contains legal papers, correspondence, and clippings relating to Karl and Stella von Kleczkowski, who was a former German espionage agent in Turkey who turned to the Allied cause in 1943.
Diplomats -- Turkey; World War, 1939-1945 -- Middle East; World War, 1939-1945 -- Turkey; Middle East -- Politics and government -- 1914-1945; Turkey -- History -- 1918-1960; Turkey -- Foreign relations; United States -- Foreign relations -- 1945-; United States -- Foreign relations -- Turkey; Photographs; Britt, George, 1895-1988; United States. Office of War Information; Steinhardt, Laurence A. (Laurence Adolph), 1892-1950
- Britt papers
  - OWI Photographs (Personal) (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - OWI Photographs (Beirut) (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - OWI Photographs (Personal) (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - OWI Photographs (Istanbul and Personal) (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence -- Harold Guinzburg (1 of 2) -- 16 Sept. 1942 -- 27 Dec. 1942 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence -- Harold Guinzburg (2 of 2) -- 30 Dec. 1942 -- 20 March 1943 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Outpost Service Bureau and James Linen Correspondence (1 of 2) -- 27 March 1943 -- 29 May 1943 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Outpost Service Bureau and James Linen Correspondence (2 of 2) 5 June 1943 -- 14 Aug. 1943 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence -- American Embassy -- 14 Sept. 1943 -- 2 Aug. 1944 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Journal Entries -- 5 Sept. 1942 -- 15 Oct. 1944 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - OWI Reports -- Syria, Lebanon, Turkey -- 14 Feb. 1943 -- 13 June 1944 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Reports -- Turkey -- 1 Sept. 1944 -- 4 Nov. 1944 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Syria and Lebanon -- 1 Feb. 1943 -- 8 Oct. 1943 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Correspondence and Reports -- 27 Aug. 1943 -- 6 June 1944 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Correspondence and Reports -- 10 Sept. 1943 -- 31 Oct. 1944 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Reports on German Propaganda in Turkey -- March -- Oct. 1944 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Rumanian Period Materials -- 12 Jan.1944 -- 24 Jan. 1945 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Newspaper List -- Lebanon and Syria -- July 1943 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Rumor Factory -- 31 Dec. 1942 -- 9 Sept. 1943 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Britt -- War Service Appointment Record -- 6 July 1942 -- 14 Dec. 1942 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - OWI Personnel Records -- May 1943 -- May 1944 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Financial Information -- 14 Sept 1945 -- 14 Nov. 1953 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Folder 23: Britt's Passport (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Miscellaneous Materials (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Turkish Marionettes (Jointed Figures) (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Karl and Stella Kleczkowski (1 of 3) -- 31 Aug. 1942 -- 9 July 1945 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Karl and Stella Kleczkowski (2 of 3) -- 15 Oct. 1945 -- 26 Jan. 1946 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Karl and Stella Kleczkowski (3 of 3) -- 1 Feb. 1946 -- 19 Dec. 1948 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Declassified correspondence (formerly marked "Secret," "Restricted," or "Confidential)," 1944 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Photographs (Box 2-3)
  - Photographs; Clippings (Box 4)